Guide to the Alexander Mordecai Bickel Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alexander Mordecai Bickel papers
1916-1987
1930-1975
MS 762
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
47.13
(109 boxes)
The papers of Alexander M. Bickel include correspondence; writings, both published and unpublished; memoranda on legislation and government policy; papers from his legal practice; papers relating to his teaching at the Yale Law School; and personal papers and photographs. Bickel's writings as well as his legal cases reflect his general political position as a classical liberal, and revolve around such issues as segregation in the schools, racial discrimination, the role of the Supreme Court in American life and politics, separation of powers, freedom of the press, and freedom of speech. From 1958 until his death, Bickel often assisted in drafting social legislation. As the papers document, most prominent among these efforts was his share in the school desegregation legislation (1970-1974). His interest in the reform of the Democratic Party is shown in such materials as drafts of testimony before the Credentials Committee of the Party (1968). His active support for Charles H. Percy in 1967 and Robert F. Kennedy in 1968 is shown by substantive correspondence and memoranda from these years. As an editor of The New Republic he wrote on legal and political issues, contributing many signed and unsigned editorials and articles. His extensive writing and reviewing for other popular magazines and in monograph form are supported in the papers with correspondence and drafts. His service in the U. S. Army during World War II and his work with the High Commissioner for Germany and the State Department in the early 1950s are also documented.
Bickel, Alexander M.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Joanne Bickel and Jeannette Hopkins, 1976; Elias Clark, 1982; Boris Bittker, 1984; Joanne Bickel, 1995; and Jeannette Hopkins, 1996. Transfer from Yale Law Library, 1989. All material except Accession 1995-M-136 have been incorporated into the series arrangement of the collection.
Arrangement
Arranged in thirteen series and one addition: I. Correspondence, 1950-1975. II. Books, 1956-1977. III. Shorter Writings, 1954-1974. IV. Public Speaking, 1956-1974. V. Senate Judiciary, 1967-1974. VI. Legislation, 1958-1974. VII. Politics, 1967-1969. VIII. Committees, 1966-1974. IX. Conferences, 1967-1972. X. Legal Practice, 1950-1974. XI. Teaching, 1956-1975. XII. State Department, 1950-1954. XIII. Memorabilia, 1941-1976.
Scope and Contents
The Alexander M. Bickel Papers consist of eighty-four archives boxes of letters, notes, drafts, and printed and near-print matter related to his work in scholarship, journalism, teaching, politics, government, and law. All phases of his career are well represented from his editing of Brandeis's Unpublished Opinions to the posthumous publication of The Morality of Consent except that few items document his classroom work. His earlier activities in law and diplomacy are represented thinly or not at all, and there is nothing antedating his clerkship with Judge Magruder.
Biographical / Historical
Alexander Mordecai Bickel, professor in Yale Law School and contributing editor of The New Republic, was a pre-eminent scholarly and popular authority on the Constitution, the Supreme Court, and the roles of the several branches of government in shaping public policy. Speaking and writing as teacher, scholar, lawyer, journalist, Democrat, and adviser to government officials, he was in the 1960s and early 1970s an important contributor to national discussion of such legal and political subjects as school desegregation, reapportionment, the Electoral College, the interpretation of the First Amendment, the powers of the President, the significance of the Warren Court, and the meaning of the liberal tradition. These are among the principal events in his personal and professional life:
1924 born in Bucharest, Rumania, to Shlomo and Yetta Bickel.
1939 immigrated with family to New York City, where his father became a journalist in the Yiddish-language press.
1943-1945 served in the U.S Army.
1947 received the B.S. in Social Science from the City College of New York.
1949 received the LL.B. from Harvard Law School,
1949-1950 served as law clerk to Chief Judge Calvert Magruder, U.S. Court of Appeals, First Circuit.
1950-1951 employed in the Office of the U.S. High Commissioner in Germany.
1951-1952 belonged to the U.S. Observer Delegation to the European Defense Community Conference in Paris.
1952-1953 served as law clerk to Associate Justice Felix Frankfurter, U.S. Supreme Court.
1953-1954 employed as special assistant to Director Robert R. Bowie, Policy Planning Staff, U.S. State Department.
1954-1956 employed as research associate, Harvard Law School.
1956 appointed associate professor, Yale Law School.
1957 chosen by the Permanent Committee for the Oliver Wendell Holmes Devise to write "Responsible Government and the Judiciary, 1910-1930," a segment of its projected Supreme Court history.
1957 published The Unpublished Opinions of Mr. Justice Brandeis.
1959-1960 lived in Washington, D.C., during most of sabbatical year.
1959 married Josephine Ann (Joanne) Napolino.
1960 appointed professor, Yale Law School.
1960 first child born, Francesca Ann.
1962 second child born, Claudia Rose.
1963 published The Least Dangerous Branch: The Supreme Court at the Bar of Politics.
1965 published Politics and the Warren Court.
1966 appointed Chancellor Kent Professor of Law and Legal History in Yale Law School and Yale University.
1966 taught in summer session, Stanford Law School.
1967 appointed consultant to the Subcommittee on the Separation of Powers, U.S. Senate Committee on the Judiciary.
1968 served on the Democratic Party's Commission on the Democratic Selection of Presidential Nominees (Hughes Commission).
1968 published The New Age of Political Reform: The Electoral College, the Convention, and the Party System.
1969 appointed consultant to the Democratic Party's Commission on Party Structure and Delegate Selection (McGovern Commission).
1969 delivered Holmes Lectures at Harvard Law School.
1970-1974 collaborated with U.S. Representative Richardson Preyer on legislation related to school desegregation.
1970 published The Supreme Court and the Idea of Progress
1970 appointed William C. DeVane Professor, Yale University, for a three-year term (1971-1974).
1970-1971 held a fellowship in the Center for Advanced Study in the Behavorial Sciences, Palo Alto, California,
1971 published Reform and Continuity: The Electoral College, the Convention, and the Party System, a revision of The New Age of Political Reform.
1971 argued for the defense in New York Times Co. v. United States (the Pentagon papers case).
1971-1973 participated in the Study Group of the Federal Judicial Center on the Caseload of the Supreme Court.
1973 published The Caseload of the Supreme Court: And What, If Anything, to Do About It.
1973 Dec underwent surgery.
1974 Feb returned to professional activity.
1974 Jul appointed Sterling Professor of Law, Yale Law School.
1974 Jul suffered relapse.
1974 Oct completed manuscript of The Morality of Consent.
1974 Nov died.
Law -- Political aspects; Law; Political conventions; Segregation in education -- Law and legislation -- United States; United States -- Foreign relations; United States -- Politics and government; Educators; Lawyers; Abrams, Floyd; Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971; Bard, Robert L.; Berns, Walter, 1919-2015; Bickel, Alexander M.; Bork, Robert H., 1927-2012; Brown, Ernest J. (Ernest Joseph), 1906-2001; Chayes, Abram Joseph, 1922-; Cowan, Arthur W. A.; Deutsch, Jan Ginter; Ellsberg, Daniel, 1931-; Elman, Philip; Freund, Paul A. (Paul Abraham), 1908-1992; Friendly, Henry Jacob, 1903-; Garment, Leonard, 1924-2013; Gunther, Gerald, 1927-2002; Harnik, Hans; Hughes, Graham, 1928-; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968; Kluger, Richard, 1934-; Kristol, Irving; Kurland, Philip B.; Lemann, Stephen B.; Levin, Betsy; Lewis, Anthony, 1927-2013; Magruder, Calvert, 1893-1968; Mishkin, Paul J.; Moynihan, Daniel P. (Daniel Patrick), 1927-2003; Packer, Herbert Leslie, 1925-1972; Pollak, Louis H.; Polsby, Nelson W., 1934-; Rostow, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1913-2002; Sacks, Albert M. (Albert Martin), 1920-1991; Stevens, Robert Bocking, 1933-; Weiner, Frederick Bernays, 1906-; United States. Supreme Court; American Bar Association; Jewish Community Center (New Haven, Conn.); Yale Law School; Yale University -- Faculty
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1953-1975; Series I; 5 linear feet (12 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, consists of several thousand letters and a few memoranda, of conversations arranged in three sections: Incoming, Outgoing, and Invitations Refused. The outgoing correspondence is fragmentary before 1960. The incoming and outgoing letters have been separated and differently arranged to facilitate retrieval by subject (as suggested by the chronology of Bickel's preoccupations) as well as correspondent. But the papers in this series constitute, at most, a large fraction of the correspondence found in Bickel's files after his death. Many letters have been placed in other series because they belong to the record of some special activity. Cross-references in the folder listing for the Incoming section of this series make it possible to locate these by writer except in the case of routine exchanges with editors, secretaries, conference organizers, and congressional committee staff. Requests to speak in public or write for publication that Bickel did not accept have been set aside as Invitations Refused along with his replies.
  Bickel's varied career before he began teaching at Yale brought him a lasting acquaintance with several prominent men in American law and government. Among his earliest correspondents were Felix Frankfurter, associate justice of the United States Supreme Court; Dean Acheson, former Secretary of State; Calvert Magruder, chief judge of the United States Court of Appeals, First Circuit; and Robert R. Bowie, director of the State Department's Policy Planning Staff and later Assistant Secretary of State. But the letters of these men remaining among his papers may not be of great value to students of their careers. The most important are Acheson's recollections of his participation in United Mine Workers v. Coronado and Duplex v. Deering as law clerk to Justice Brandeis (1955 Dec 7, 1964 May 27). Bickel gave Frankfurter's letters to Harvard Law School, leaving behind only a few memoranda and some slip opinions, and the Magruder and Bowie letters have little substance. The only letter from John J. McCloy, under whom Bickel served when he was High Commissioner in Germany, is a note transmitting a recent speech.
  As Bickel's reputation grew, members of Congress became interested in his opinions, and his correspondence broadened accordingly. Many of the longest and most important sequences of letters in this category have been placed in Series V-VIII. What remains in this series are mainly isolated requests for Bickel's opinion. A few of these letters, such as those by Senators Birch Bayh, Edward M. Kennedy, and Joseph Tydings, bespeak a continuing association, but neither these inquiries nor the occasional form letters from other members of Congress add much to the public record of the writers' activities and opinions.
  Bickel was also a friend or occasional correspondent of several members of the Nixon administration. The letters of Daniel P. Moynihan, assistant for urban affairs and ambassador to the United Nations, and Leonard Garment, adviser on civil rights, show that both men provided a channel of communication between Bickel and the President. Other letters of Nixon aides can be found in Series VI. The significance of Bickel's association with Nixon appointees outside the White House is more difficult to estimate. All the correspondence with his friend Robert Bork occurred before he was named Solicitor General, and most of the letters by cabinet member Elliot Richardson merely acknowledge congratulations on his successive appointments. Bickel was also acquainted with men serving in the three previous administrations, but the letters they exchanged provide no evidence of access to the president or influence on his ideas. Texts of speeches accompany the letters of Moynihan, Donald F. Turner, and several other presidential appointees.
  Many other incoming letters were written by Bickel's professional colleagues, a few working in the federal government but most teaching or practicing law. These tended to be personal associations as well, and the subjects are correspondingly mixed. Exchanges of ideas and of first-hand information about historically important events are far less common than reports of personal news and transactions of routine professional business, but there are a few exceptions. The letters of Philip Elman include a recollection of the Rosenberg case (1966 Jan 20, after he had left the Solicitor General's Office) and several observations about his work as Federal Trade Commissioner. The letters of Eugene V. Rostow include discriminating reactions to Bickel's writings, lengthy expressions of opinion on domestic and foreign policy questions, and texts, of speeches and essays. Those of Frederick B. Wiener are rich in comment on current legal and political events. Among the federal judiciary, Bickel's principal correspondent was Henry J. Friendly, chief judge of the United States Court of Appeals, Second Circuit, whose letters contain favorable comments on Bickel's writings and other expressions of esteem.
  The major letters in the Outgoing section are those containing lengthy comments on issues of the day, most addressed to public officials but a few composed for the benefit of friends and colleagues. Most of these were written in response to requests for his opinion. Among the topics are passport regulation (1959 Jul 8, to Senator J. William Fulbright), the presidential succession (1964 Jan 27, to Senator Hubert Humphrey), legislation to limit court-ordered reapportionment (1967 Jun 6, to Senator Howard Baker), judicial rule-making (1970 Jan 22, to Dean Acheson), and congressional imposition of a moratorium on the death penalty (1971 May 6, to Senator Philip Hart). Many of the subjects thus treated he also discussed in The New Republic, and some were the focus of special activities documented in other series, but a letter in this series sometimes provides an earlier expression of his ideas. Other outgoing letters mix personal news and routine business in the manner of the incoming letters from friends and colleagues. Bickel rarely discussed with outsiders the details of important events in which he participated, but his letters do afford a few observations about the preliminaries to the Supreme Court decision in Brown v. Board of Education (e.g., 1955 Dec 8, 1967 Sep 22, 1971 Mar 18).
  Arrangement
  Incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically by writer. Letters are ordered chronologically for each writer. Cross-references consisting only of a name refer to the appropriate location in this section. Cross-references to other series refer to a section or folder in that series. Where the cross-reference is to another series, the items are not necessarily noted on the folder listing but must be located by examining the contents of the folder or folders. Outgoing correspondence is arranged chronologically. Invitations Refused are arranged alphabetically by the name of the institution or person extending the invitation. The correspondence connected with each invitation is in chronological order. Folders with asterisks(*) contain ten or more items.
  - Incoming
    - Ab - Ad (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Al (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Am - Ay (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Abrams, Floyd(*), 1960-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      General
      See also: box 53, folder 120 See also: box 57, folder 161
    - Acheson, David, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Acheson, Dean(*), 1955-1957, 1964,1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      See also: box 26, folder 14
    - Advisory Council on Appellate Justice
      See: box 36, folder 6 See: box 36, folders 12-13
    - "The Advocates", 1970, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ainsworth, Robert A., 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Allen, Louis C., Jr.
      See: box 32, folder 13 See: box 32, folder 15 See: box 32, folder 17
    - Alsop, Joseph, 1969, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Alternative, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - American Bar Association(*), 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - American Bar Association, Special Committee on Coordination of Judicial Improvements, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      See also: box 37, folder 17
    - American Civil Liberties Union, 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      See also: box 5, folder 106 See also: box 45, folder 28 See also: box 45, folder 34
    - American Histadrut Cultural Exchange Institute, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - American Jewish Committee, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      See also: box 1, folder 22
    - American Jewish Congress, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      See also: box 5, folder 104 See also: box 7, folder 118
    - Anastaplo, George, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Anderson, John B., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      See also: box 33, folder 28
    - Andrews, Earl O., 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith, 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      See also: box 46, folder 43
    - Arnold, Thurman
      See: box 26, folder 11
    - Ashmore, Harry S.
      See: box 21, folder 85
    - Association of American Law Schools, 1961-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Auerbach, Jerold S.
      See: box 37, folder 30
    - Ba (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Be (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bi (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bl (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bn - Bo (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bra - Bron (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Broo - Bu (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Baker, Howard H., Jr., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Banzhaf, John F., III
      See: box 32, folder 5
    - Bard, Robert L.(*), 1961-1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Bartley, Robert L., 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Baskir, Lawrence M.
      See: box 30, folder 1-3
    - Bator, Paul M., 1958-1974
      See also: box 7, folder 136
    - Baxter, William F., 1966
      See also: box 70, folder 67
    - Bayh, Birch, 1965, 1969-1973,undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - The Benchers, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Berger, Raoul, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Berns, Walter F.(*), 1961-1964, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Bernstein, Merton C., 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Berry, Mary F.
      See: box 39, folder 61
    - Beytagh, Francis X.
      See: box 36, folder 10
    - Bishop, Joseph W., Jr., 1956-1960, 1971
    - Bittker, Boris I., 1957, 1967-1973, undated
      See also: box 23, folder 135
    - Black, Charles L., Jr., 1959-1960, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Black, Hugo, 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Black American Law Students Association
      See: box 2, folder 36
    - Blumstein, James F., 1967-1974 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - The Bobbs-Merrill Company
      See: box 4, folder 73
    - Bok, Derek, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Bookbinder, Hyman, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Bork, Ellen (daughter of Robert H.), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Bork, Robert H.(*), 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      See also: box 14, folder 45 See also: box 15, folder 67
    - Borroff, Marie, 1968-1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Bowerman, Richard H.
      See: box 1, folder 19
    - Bowie, Robert R., 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      See also: box 74, folder 1
    - Brandeis, Elizabeth
      See: box 7, folder 12
    - Brandeis, Susan
      See:box 3, folder 63
    - Brewster, Kingman, 1954, 1962-1971 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Brown, Ernest J.(*), 1958-1974 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      See also: box 32, folder 2
    - Brown, Ralph S., 1967, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Buckley, William F., Jr., 1973 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      See also: box 45, folder 28 See also: box 45, folder 34
    - Bundy, McGeorge
      See: box 41, folder 7
    - Bunzel, John H., 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      See also: box 29, folder 52
    - Burger, Warren E., 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      See also: box 37, folder 21 See also: box 36, folder 1
    - Burling, Edward B.
      See: box 5, folder 94
    - Burt, Robert A., 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Burton, Harold H., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - CBS - Cal (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Cam - Ce (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Ch - Cl (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Coa - Col (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Com - Coo (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Cor - Cu (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Calabresi, Guido, 1966, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - California Rural Legal Assistance, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Campbell, Thomas P.
    - Cappalli, Richard B., 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      See also: box 52, folders 99-101
    - Casper, Gerhard, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Celler, Emanuel
      See: box 3, folder 55 See: box 21, folder 98 See: box 33, folder 24
    - Chayes, Abram J.(*), 1956-1970 (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
    - Chayes, Antonia (Mrs. Abram), 1957, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Chayes, Edward (brother of Abram), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Chertoff, Mordecai S.
      See: box 1, folder 9
    - Chicago, University of
      See: box 6, folder 111
    - Christopher, Warren, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Clark, Eli, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Coalition for a Democratic Majority
      See: box 2, folder 44 See: box 3, folder 49
    - Cochran, Otis C., 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Coffin, Catherine (Mrs. William S., Jr.), 1968 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Coffin, William S., Jr., 1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      See also: box 55, folder 143
    - Cohelan, Jeffery, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Coleman, William T., Jr., 1965, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Colson, Charles W., 1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Commentary, 1957-1974 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Commission on Party Structure and Delegate Selection
      See: box 38, folder 39
    - Commission on Rules
      See: box 40, folder 67
    - Commission on the Democratic Selection of Presidential Nominees
      See: box 38, folder 34 See: box 38, folder 39
    - Congress of Racial Equality
      See: box 53, folders 117-118
    - Connecticut Commission for Standards of Decency in Materials Available for Sale to the Public, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Connecticut Secretary of the State, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Cooke, David
      See: box 34, folder 41
    - Corcoran, Thomas G., 1973 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Corwin, Edward S., 1957 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Cousins, Norman
      See: box 3, folder 47
    - Cowan, Arthur W. A.(*), 1954-1963 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      See also: box 53, folder 117
    - Cowan, Geoffrey
      See: box 38, folder 38
    - Cramton, Roger
      See: box 36, folder 2
    - Crangle, Joseph F.
    - Craven, J. Braxton, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Curzan, Myron P.
      See: box 32, folder 7
    - Cutler, Lloyd N., 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      See also: box 48, folder 63
    - Da (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - De (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Di - Don (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Doo - Dr (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Du (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Danaher, John A., 1971 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Danelski, David
      See: box 39, folder 59 See: box 39, folder 61
    - Danzig, Richard, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - David, Paul T.